A Guide to the Papers of Henry James Brown 1829-1884
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Henry James Brown 1829-1884
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9930
This collection contains 114 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of Mrs. Janet Worsham Roller, granddaughter of Henry James Brown, through her nephew, Charles Worsham, on January 16, 1974.
Alternative Form
Also available on microfilm on reel #M-2334.
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry James Brown was born October 12, 1811 in Cumberland Co., Virginia. His interest in painting developed at age sixteen when his family was having portraits made by an itinerant painter. Brown did not like his portrait and when he attempted to improve on it, he was quite successful. He continued to paint and draw in the evenings after he had finished his farm work.
In 1833, Brown married Susan Ann Hobson. They lived in Sunnyside, Virginia, until 1837 when they moved to Miami, Missouri. Brown became a very successful hemp farmer and he spent more and more of his time painting. In 1841, he met George Caleb Bingham. The two men became good friends who traveled and painted together in the West for a few years. In 1847, Brown left his farm in the care of an overseer and moved his family back to Virginia.
At this point in his life, he did not have to worry about making a living, so he devoted most of his time to painting. In 1848, he met Thomas Sully and was invited to spend several months as a student in Sully's studio in Philadelphia. In 1849 he became involved with the Female Collegiate Institute in Buckingham County and served as Vice-President of its Board of Directors. Although he spent a great deal of time insuring the success and solvency of the college, he continued his painting. His career came to an abrupt end in 1854 when he died of typhoid pneumonia.
For further information, see the addition to this collection: Henry James Brown: American Artist, His Life and Works, a M.A. thesis written by Charles E. Worsham in 1969 (9930-a).
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of correspondence and a diary containing accounts, sketches and personal notes of Henry James Brown and William S. Brown; his sister, Nancy Brown; his wife, Susan Ann Hobson Brown; the commercial concerns, Dibrell and Jones Co., and Ensign and Sears Co., and his personal friends, Henry Gordon, John C. Hobson, Willis W. Hobson, Robert Ruxton and Thomas Sully.
Contents List
- Nancy H. Brown to Henry James Brown April 11, 1829, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Daniel Brown to HJB June 17, 1829, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Nancy Brown to HJB September 4, (1829), ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- W.W. Turner to HJB January 27, 1831, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- B. Whitlow to HJB March 27, 1831, Acct., 1 p., w/dkt.
- Robert Brown to HJB March 3, 1839, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Receipt, Wilson and Brown September 19, 1839, AN, 1 p.
- Duensinberry and Darlington to HJB October 7, 1839, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Post Office Department appointment of Robert Brown December 23, 1839, DS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Wilson & Brown to R. W. Brown April 14, 1840, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wilson & Brown to R. W. Brown May 7, 1840, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- R. W. Brown to "Dear Brother" November 7, 1840, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Elizabeth Brown & Robert W. Brown to HJB December 10, 1840, ALS, 4 p., incl/addr.
- Wm. S. Worsham to Mrs. Henningham E. Worsham February 18, 1843, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Fitzhugh Coyle to Robert W. Brown (printed form completed by hand) September 3, 1845, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- J. H. Irvin to the 2nd Auditor, P.O. Dept., Washington, D.C. August 5, 1847, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB October 30, 1847, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton December 27, 1847, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Susan A. Brown to her husband, HJB April 11, (1848), ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Susan A. Brown to her husband, HJB April 25, (1848), ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB May 17, 1848, ALS, 2 p., incl/addr.
- John B. H. Woolridge to HJB May 31, 1848, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB June 26, 1848, ALS, 4 p., incl/addr.
- HJB to Chandler, Howard & Co. July 10, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB July 26, 1848, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB August 15, 1848, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Chandler, Howard & Co. to HJB August 15, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Poem by (O. Philo?) to HJB August 21, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Chandler, Howard & Co. to HJB September 7, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Chandler, Howard & Co. to HJB October 23, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- L. Weedin to HJB November 4, 1848, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB November 17, 1848, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Receipt, (B.W.H.F.?) to HJB December 9, 1848, ANS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB December 14, 1848, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Thomas Sully to HJB December 17, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- J. Kean to HJB December 20, 1848, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB February 1, 1849, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Ernest Franck to HJB April 27, 1849, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Howard, Son & Co. to HJB, w/ attachment, "Boston Prices Current" May 2, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.; pntd., 2 p.
- (M.W.F.?) to Daniel Brown May 6, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB June 22, 1849, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Howard, Son & Co. to HJB June 23, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB July 4, 1849, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- (?) & Co. to HJB July 6, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Ernest Franck to HJB July 16, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB August 25, 1849, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Howard, Son & Co. to HJB, w/ attachment, "Boston Prices Current" August 31, 1849, and August 29, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.; pntd., 2 p.
- Howard, Son & Co. to HJB (enclosing statement of account) September 19, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr., 1 p.
- Ernest Franck to HJB October 3, 1849, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- R. R. Duval to HJB November 24, 1849, ANS, 1 p., w/addr.
- J. M. Hearants to HJB January 16, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB January 17, 1850, ALS, 3 p.
- Robert Ruxton to HJB January 29, 1850, ALS, 4 p., incl/addr.
- Ernest Franck to HJB March 13, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Thomas C. Hayes to HJB August 28, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
- F. H. Larkin & Co. to HJB, w/ attachment, "Saint Louis Price-Current and Commercial Record" September 4, 1850; August 31, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/addr., and 2 p.
- Ernest Franck to HJB October 7, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- W. W. Bennett to HJB December 6, 1850, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- W. S. Morton to HJB December 7, 1850, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- J. C. Hobson to HJB January 4, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- B. R. Duval to HJB January 20, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Edward Brown to HJB April 12, 1851, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Nash & Woodhouse to HJB April 17, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- John B. Turner April 19, 1851, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Willis W. Hobson to HJB April 28, 1851, ALS, 1 p.
- F. H. Larkin & Co. to HJB June 25, 1851, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
- Henry Gordon to HJB July 21, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Samuel R. Irvine to HJB August 25, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB November 1, 1851, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- J. T. Jackson to HJB November 27, 1851, ANS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Executrix, estate of Wm. C. Styles, to HJB November 28, 1851, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB January 5, 1852, ALS, 4 p.
- John C. Hobson to HJB (business card, Underhill & Lloyd, attached) February 19, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB February 19, 1852, ALS, 4 p.
- John C. Hobson to HJB March 4, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- B. A. Brown, receipt to HJB March 10, 1852, ANS, 1 p.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB April 27, 1852, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
- A. S. H. Gordon to HJB July 7, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- H(enry) Gordon to HJB July 16, 1852, ANS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Dibrell & Jones to HJB August 17, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- B. A. Brown, receipt to HJB August 19, 1852, ANS, 1 p., w/dkt.
- R(obert) Ruxton to HJB August 24, 1852, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Dibrell & Jones to HJB August 30, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
- Giles Harris to HJB September 13, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- HJB to "Ann" (Susan Ann Hobson Brown) September 16, 1852, ALS, 2 p.
- F. W. Hobson to "Henry" (HJB) September 18, 1852, ALS, 1 p.
- Ensign & Sears to HJB September 20, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Dibrell & Jones to HJB September 21, 1852, ALS, 2 p., w/addr.
- Fredric W. Hobson to HJB September 23, 1852, ALS, 2 p., w/env.
- Barksdale & Read to HJB Novemebr 23, 1852, ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Lancaster Harris & Co. to HJB December 4, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- A. Preot to HJB December 10, 1852, ALS, 2 p.
- Isaac Adams to HJB December 31, 1852, ALS, 1 p.
- W. S. Wising to HJB January 6, 1853, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
- Ensign & Sears to HJB (enclosing statement of account) January 17, 1853, ALS, 1 p., w/env.; 1 p.
- Frederic W. Hobson to HJB, w/ attachment, "Merchants' Prices-Current and Shipping List" January 22, 1853 and January 20, 1853, ALS, 2 p.; pntd., 2 p.
- Dibrell & Jones to HJB, w/ attachment, "Merchnats' Prices-Current and Shipping List" and enclosing 1853 Feb 10 statement of account February 11, 1853 and February 3, 1853, ANS, 1 p., w/addr.; 2 p.; 1 p.
- Wm. S. Brown to HJB November 23, 1853, ALS, 1 p., w/env.
- Betty Hatcher to Susan A. Brown August 3, (1860), ALS, 3 p., w/env.
- Peyton A. Brown to "Dear Mama" August 16, 1860, ALS, 2 p.
- "Sister Jennie" to Salina J. Brown August 22, 1860, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
- Frederick (Pransford?) to HJB August 16, 1852, ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- Charlotte V. Hatcher to "Cousin Ann" September 1, 1862, ALS, 2 p.
- W. S. Brown to Susan Ann Brown December 1, 1865, ALS, 3 p., w/env.
- Mary C. Shields to Joseph Worsham May 20, 1884, ALS, 4 p., w/env.
- "Ella" to "Dear Aunt" October 30, n.y., ALS, 2 p.
- J. H. Irvin to (HJB) December 1, n.y., ALS, 3 p., w/addr.
- Wilson & Brown to R. W. Brown n.d., ALS, 1 p., w/addr.
- addressed to HJB n.d., 4 items, envs.
- Diary by William S. Brown containing notes, sketches, and accounts re: a trip from Virginia to Missouri ca. 1844, AMs, 54 p.
- "Brother's trip from Va. to Mo." (on the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad) n.d., AMs, 5 p.
- "Saint Louis Price-Current and Commercial Record" April 23, 1853, pntd., 2 p.
- Newspaper clippings of (Civil War) poems, sent to Susan A. Brown n.d., pntd., 6 items.
- Ballot for Cumberland Co., Va. n.d., pntd., 1 p.